Hey everyone, welcome to another lesson
in the Stoska automation course.
In the previous session, we talked about
recovery scenarios. How you can recover
your test cases from an unexpected
failure or error. But before I continue,
I must say you have to watch the
previous session in order to understand
this session better because these two
topics are quite related. So if you
don't understand how recovery scenarios
work, you won't understand how cleanup
scenarios would be working. Right? So
coming back to recovery scenarios, when
we employ a recovery scenario and the
application state now changes so that it
can recover out of unexpected failure,
right? But what if this recovery also
fails? So tosska is not able to recover
out of that error and now it is stuck in
a state from where it cannot continue.
So your all your test steps which
continue after this uh failed test step
would also fail because the application
is in a state from where it cannot
execute those test steps. Right?
So to resolve this problem toka also
provides you an additional option called
cleanup scenarios. Now it is also part
of the recovery engine. So when the
recovery scenarios fail, it goes into
this cleanup scenarios and you can
define your own test steps to bring the
application back to the original state.
So for example, if um you are closing
and opening the application in your
recovery scenario, right? And uh it is
not able to open the application. So all
your test steps of continuing after this
will fail. Right? So in this case what
you can do you can put some test steps
which can go back and launch the
application login into that page and go
to that particular page from where it
will continue the next steps. Right? So
all these test steps you can mention in
the cleanup scenarios.
So let's uh take it little further and
let's try to understand with our
original example where we employed our
recovery scenario right so we employed
our recovery scenario on this page where
we were trying to click on the submit
button and it takes around few seconds
to enable this right so we had put a
recovery scenario to wait on this button
until this is enabled and then it will
click right so that way we were able to
recover uh from an unexpected failure.
Okay.
Now think of a scenario. We want to
click on the next link, right? Which is
open new page. So on clicking this link,
it opens the same page in a different
tab. Okay? But uh what is the scenario
is if the submit button is still not
enabled, right? You cannot go ahead and
click on this link unless you reopen the
application and then you will be able to
directly click on this open new page.
Okay. So that's that's the kind of
scenario which is present in front of
you. Now I'm just trying to relate uh to
this recovery and cleanup scenarios so
that you can understand uh this
scenarios better and you can employ it
same into your application whenever you
face this kind of scenarios right.
So uh in this kind of scenario what we
can do is even if our recovery fails to
click on this button right uh we go
ahead and put two steps where we close
the page and reopen this page so that
this open new page link is now enabled
and we can click on it directly. Okay.
So we don't have to go through this
loop. We uh do a different way of
clicking on this page. So we bring back
the application to its original state.
Okay.
So this is what our scenario is. Now
let's go to TSA and see how we can
implement a cleanup scenarios. Okay.
So you have to have a recovery scenario
in order to add a cleanup scenario.
Okay. So when you have created this
recovery scenarios folder right the
parent folder right click on it and you
will see there is a icon where it tells
create cleanup scenario okay you can
also use the shortcuts CtrlN and Ctrl C
okay so click on that and then it will
create a cleanup scenario okay and
inside this we can add our steps so what
I want is I want to close the page and I
want to reopen on the page. Okay. So
I can directly go here and I can copy
this test steps into this cleanup
scenario. So I first want to close the
URL and then I want to open the URL. So
I will just copy it here and paste it
here. Right? So I have two test steps
now in cleanup scenario. Close URL and
open URL. And this will bring back my
application to its original state from
which then it can continue to execute
the other test steps. Right? Which is to
open new page and then it will uh
finally close it or any other test
steps. Right? The main idea is if the
recovery scenario fails, we also have a
cleanup scenario where we can bring back
our application to its original state.
Okay. So that's the main idea.
Now uh let's go ahead and execute this
right and see whether it works or not.
Now if you have created your execution
list and you are making some changes to
your test cases right just to be sure
that these changes are also reflecting
in your execution list. You can right
click on it and click on synchronize.
Right? So it will synchronize the
changes between the test cases and the
execution list. Okay. Now let's go ahead
and click on run. Okay. And let's see
whether it works or not.
So in this particular scenario, it is
going to fail the test step and the
recovery scenario. And in that
particular case, it is going to employ
the cleanup scenario. If you have
noticed in the screen, it has reopened
this application, right? And after that,
it is going ahead and performing the
test steps which could have been blocked
if there was no cleanup scenario. Okay.
So, let's go ahead and look at these
logs, right? So, let's go into this
submit log and this is the current
execution. So, you see this submit
enabled this uh this is failed this test
step. The recovery scenario has also
failed. Okay.
But after this recovery scenario has
failed, it has now enabled this cleanup
scenario. Right. So it has gone into
this cleanup scenario and it has closed
the URL, opened the URL. Basically, it
has executed this test steps. Okay.
After this was done, now it went ahead
with the remaining test steps. Right.
So combining both cleanup scenarios and
recovery scenarios, you can ideally come
out of unexpected failures or errors
from which your execution can still
continue. Even if there are failures,
your execution will not stop, right? So
that way you can have a better execution
cycle because uh then you can look at
those failures and go ahead and fix
them. But at least your execution will
go ahead and it is not stuck if your
recovery scenario fails or if your test
step fails. Right?
So this was all about cleanup scenarios.
Hope uh it was useful for you. We would
come up with another interesting topic
next Friday. So keep watching and do
subscribe to our channel. We also have a
webinar on uh tricentis tosskut live
training going ahead on this Sunday the
6th of November. So if you are
interested please go ahead and register
at our site www.qascript.com.